Lillian Thomas Pratt Personal Papers, 1917-1967, n.d.
VMFA Archives, Virginia Museum of Fine Arts
Lillian Thomas Pratt Personal Papers
1917-1967, n.d.
Special Collection 07 (SC-07): Digital Collection
VMFA Archives, Virginia Museum of Fine Arts
2 boxes (15 folders), 1 binder and 41 items
Pratt, Lillian B. 1876?
This collection documents the formation of the Lillian Thomas Pratt Collection of Fabergé decorative artworks at the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts. Bequeathed to the museum upon her death in 1947, Pratt’s Fabergé collection consistently remains one of the highlights of the museum’s permanent collection. Pratt purchased most of her Fabergé collection from the Schaffer Collection and Hammer Galleries, both of New York City, in the 1930's and 1940's. Comprised of correspondence, invoices, price tags, and detailed item descriptions, this collection illuminates Pratt’s mind as a collector, as well as her relationship with one of her dealers, Alexander Schaffer. This collection has been digitized and is.
Administrative Information
Provenance
This collection was transferred over time to the VMFA Library in the 2000's by museum staff members Dr. David Park Curry, Curator of the Fabergé collection, David Bradley, Foundation Director, and Richard Woodward, Deputy Director for Architecture and Design. The estate tax information was given to Woodward from the Honorable John D. Butzner, Jr. in the 1970's. The bulk of the collection was accessioned into the VMFA Archives’ collection in February 2011. In January 2015, an additional collection of documents were transferred from the Curatorial files to the Pratt collection.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research. Items in "Series 5: Museum Records" are represented in the digital collection, but are still physically located in their respective museum departments.
Biographical Note
Two months after Lillian Thomas Pratt’s death in June 1947, her stunning and expansive collection of Fabergé artworks were unexpectedly bequeathed to the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts. Thought to have been born in 1876 in Philadelphia, details of Pratt’s life still remain sketchy and limited. By 1900, she was working as a stenographer at the Puget Sound Flouring Mill, and in 1917, married her second husband, John Lee Pratt, a self-made millionaire engineer and businessman with General Motors. By 1931, they had settled at Chatham Manor in John’s native Virginia, and Pratt spent over a decade amassing a collection of over 500 items, eighty percent of which is Russian decorative art, mainly Fabergé.
Pratt began collecting while accompanying her husband on business trips to New York City, shopping in her spare time, and possibly becoming enchanted with the Hammer Galleries’ “Russian Imperial Exhibit” at Lord and Taylor in the early 1930s. While the total amount she spent during that time is unknown, she spent $100,000 alone at New York City’s Schaffer Collection. She simultaneously purchased items, including four of her five imperial Easter eggs, from the Hammer Galleries. Her collection includes not only the finest imperial eggs, but also miniature eggs, jewelry, framed photographs, boxes, handles, flowers, and animal figures, among many other types of objects. Whatever her collecting may have been (besides simply furnishing her new home), her fascination with Russian royalty was enduring, and has been shared with museum visitors for over 60 years.
(The above information was taken from "Fabergé: Virginia Museum of Fine Arts", 1995.)
Scope and Content Note
The collection’s inclusive dates are 1917-1967, with the bulk of the material dating from 1933-1945. The collection is comprised of correspondence, invoices, price tags, item descriptions, exhibition labels, estate tax information and inventories, photographs, drawings and newspaper clippings.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series, and items are generally arranged chronologically within each series. Price tags are arranged numerically by item number. Items with no date are placed at the end at each series:
Series 1: Schaffer Collection, 1934-1947, n.d.
Series 2: Hammer Galleries, 1933-1945, n.d.
Series 3: Estate, 1932-1947, n.d.
Series 4: Clippings, 1932-1937, n.d.
Series 5: Museum Records, 1917-1967, n.d.
Subject Terms
Pratt, Lillian Thomas, B. 1876?; Fabergé, Peter Carl, 1846-1920.; Schaffer, Alexander.; Schaffer, Ray.; Fabergé (Firm); Virginia Museum of Fine Arts.; Schaffer Collection.; Hammer Galleries.; A La Vieille Russie (Firm); Lillian Thomas Pratt Collection.; Crown Jewels--Russia (Federation)--Art collections.; Jewelry--Russia (Federation)--Art collections.; Easter eggs--Russia (Federation)--Art collections.; Goldwork--Russia (Federation)--Art collections.; Art objects--Russia (Federation)--Art collections.
Related Materials
See further information in the VMFA Library:
Catalogs:
-Imperial Russian Easter Eggs Presented by Tsar Nikolai II, 1940
-Handbook of the Lillian Thomas Pratt Collection: Russian Imperial Jewels, 1960
-Fabergé: A Catalog of the Lillian Thomas Pratt Collection of Russian Imperial Jewels, 1976
-Fabergé: Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, 1995
-Fabergé Revealed: At the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, 2011
Video:
-Lillian Thomas Pratt's Fabergé: Shopping, Collecting, Remembering, 1996/2004
Exhibition Files:
-Selections from the Lillian Thomas Pratt Collection of Jewels, 1947
-12th Anniversary Exhibition: The Pratt Collection of Jewels, 1948
-Imperial Russian Easter Eggs, 1950
-Imperial Russian Easter Eggs, 1951
-Imperial Russian Easter Eggs, 1952
-Jewelry by Fabergé, 1953
-Jewels by Fabergé, 1954
-Fabergé in America and the Lillian Thomas Pratt Collection of Fabergé, 1996
-Fabergé Revealed, 2011
Subject Files:
-VMFA Collections: Decorative Arts: Metalwork: Faberge
-VMFA Donors: Pratt, John Lee and Lillian Thomas
-VMFA Gallery Design: Faberge
See related archival records in the following institutions:
Library of Virginia:
-Virginia Museum of Fine Arts Director’s Correspondence, 1936-1976 (Coll. No. 33863 and 44067)
-Virginia Museum of Fine Arts Exhibition Files, 1936-1992 (Coll No. 31633, 32958, 33041, 33160, 34679, 36342, 36957 and 37636)
Series Descriptions/Folder Lists
- Series 1: Schaffer Collection, 1934-1947, n.d.
  Box 1 (6 Folders and 1 Binder) This series is comprised of correspondence, invoices, price tags, and item descriptions that detail the purchases Pratt made from the Schaffer collection in the 1930s and 1940s. Correspondence between Alexander S. Schaffer, his wife Ray Schaffer, and Pratt discuss sales, payments, display cabinets, family matters, and books and articles he sent to Pratt about Russian history, war, and family matters. After 1944, some of the correspondence, invoices and item descriptions came from A La Vieille Russie, where Schaffer continued to deal in Russian art and antiquities after closing his own shop. The invoices are often annotated with check numbers as balances were paid off, and dates given often refer to the handwritten notes on the invoice detailing payment history. Similarly, price tags were often annotated with price reductions or alterations in the item’s description. Item descriptions are extremely detailed, and include the item number and often the date purchased. Many of the Schaffer descriptions are not dated, and while most of them can be cross-referenced with dates on the invoices, Schaffer often invoiced Pratt much later than the original purchase date, and in some cases, many years later. Finally, most of the item descriptions were annotated by museum staff at some point with VMFA accession numbers. The series is divided into five subseries.
  - Series 1.1: Alexander Schaffer Correspondence
    - Correspondence with Alexander Schaffer, 1934-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Series 1.2: Ray Schaffer Correspondence
    - Correspondence with Ray Schaffer, 1937-1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Series 1.3: Invoices
    - Schaffer Collection Invoices, 1934-1945, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Series 1.4: Price Tags
    - Schaffer Collection Price Tags, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Schaffer Collection Envelope, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Series 1.5: Item Descriptions
    - Descriptions from Schaffer Collection, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Descriptions from Schaffer Collection, 1937-1945, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series 2: Hammer Galleries, 1933-1945, n.d.
  Box 1 (5 Folders, 1 Oversize Item and 1 Binder) This series is comprised of invoices, price tags, item descriptions, exhibition labels and correspondence that document the purchases Pratt made from the Hammer Galleries in the 1930s and 1940s. The Lord and Taylor invoices are undated, but the item numbers match up with Hammer Galleries price tags, and the Galleries did present and sell their collection at Lord and Taylor in the early 1930s (probably 1934 based upon letterhead from the item descriptions). Price tags were often annotated with price reductions or alterations in the item’s description. Item descriptions are extremely detailed, and include the item number and the date purchased. Most of the item descriptions were annotated by museum staff at some point with VMFA accession numbers. A note in Pratt’s hand is written on the item description for a traveling clock (item number 5253, purchased June 16, 1933) and says “Given to H.R.H. Princess Margaret Rose of England May 1939.” She received a letter of acknowledgment and appreciation back from Lady Constance Harriet Stuart Gaskell, a Woman of the Bedchamber to Queen Mary. Finally, the few exhibition labels were used in the Hammer Collection’s “Russian Imperial Exhibit” at Lord and Taylor. Four are still mounted on the original gold colored panels. The series is divided into five subseries.
  - Series 2.1: Lord and Taylor Invoices
    - Lord and Taylor Invoices, [1933] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Series 2.2: Price Tags
    - Hammer Galleries Price Tags, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Series 2.3: Item Descriptions
    - Descriptions from Hammer Galleries, 1933-1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Descriptions from Hammer Galleries, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Descriptions from Hammer Galleries, 1940-1945, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Series 2.4: Exhibition Labels
    - Hammer Galleries Labels, "Russian Imperial Exhibit", 1933-1934, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Series 2.5: Correspondence
    - Correspondence with Lady Gaskell, 1932-1947, n.d. (Box Flat Files)
- Series 3: Estate
  Box 2 (3 Folders and 1 Binder) This series is comprised of information about Pratt’s estate after her death on July 21, 1947. The estate tax return outlines the extent of her entire estate, including the varied philanthropic bequests and funds she had arranged. Detailed inventories of the estate list her belongings by category. One of the paintings lists was annotated by a local appraiser, Virginia Clarke Taylor, denoting which paintings were “antiques” or not. Finally, there are many price tags from other non-Faberge purchases she made over the years. Most are from the New York department store B. Altman and Company, and detail her acquisitions of silver, lamps, fabric, vases, paintings, and other decorative items. The series is divided into three subseries.
  - Series 3.1: Tax Information
    - Pratt Estate Tax Return and Memo, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Series 3.2: Inventory
    - Pratt Estate Inventory, 1947, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Series 3.3: Other Furnishings
    - Pratt Estate Furnishings Price Tags, 1932, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Pratt Estate Furnishing Item Description, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Series 4: Clippings, 1932-1947, n.d.
  Box 2 (1 Folder) This series is comprised of the few clippings that were found in the collection. As none of these particular clippings were mentioned in the correspondence directly, it’s possible that they did not originally belong to Pratt. The photographic copies of some of the articles were obviously made much later, but were retained as they may have been copies of articles Pratt once kept.
  - Clippings, 1932-1947, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Series 5: Museum Records, 1917-1967, n.d.
  15 Books and 25 Items This series is comprised of items related to the Pratt collection that are held in other museum departments. Pratt's personal library was donated to the Library upon her death, and the contents include books about Russian history and culture, as well as private editions about her collection published by Hammer Galleries. Curatorial records include early photographs of items from both Hammer Galleries and the Schaffer Collection, as well as a statement of account from Hammer and the first complete list of the collection after its arrival at the museum. Finally, images from the Photographic Archives show the public's early fascination with the collection. Especially amazing was the tradition of photographing local children handling the eggs for publicity shoots, a practice which shows just how much museum culture has changed in the second half of the 20th century. Items in this series are represented in the digital collection, but are still physically located in their respective museum departments (RB = Rare Books; CF= Curatorial Files; PH = Photographic Archives).
  - Pratt's Personal Library, 1917-1940, n.d. (Box RB)
  - Curatorial Files, 1936-1947, n.d. (Box CF)
  - Photographic Archives, 1956-1967, n.d. (Box PH)